In the great 1980s movie "The Blues Brothers,"
في فلم الثمانينيات الرائع "ذا بلوز برادورز"
there's a scene where John Belushi goes to visit Dan Aykroyd in his apartment
كان هناك مشهد حيث يزور جون بيلوشي دان أيكرويد
in Chicago for the very first time.
في شقته بشيكاغو لأول مرة.
It's a cramped, tiny space
وهي شقة غير مرتبة وصغيرة جداً
and it's just three feet away from the train tracks.
وتبعد بضعة أمتار فقط عن سكة الحديد.
As John sits on Dan's bed,
وبينما جون جالس على سرير دان،
a train goes rushing by,
مر بهما قطار مسرع
rattling everything in the room.
مسقطاً كل شيء بالغرفة.
John asks, "How often does that train go by?"
فقال جون: "كم مرة يمر بها هذا القطار في اليوم؟"
Dan replies, "So often, you won't even notice it."
أجاب دان:"بما يكفي لكي لا تشعر به."
And then, something falls off the wall.
ليسقط بعدها شيء ما من على الحائط.
We all know what he's talking about.
ونعرف جميعاً عما كان يتحدث.
As human beings, we get used to everyday things
كبشر نعتاد الأشياء اليومية
really fast.
بسرعة كبيرة.
As a product designer, it's my job to see those everyday things,
بصفتي مصمم منتجات، فإن مهمتي هي ملاحظة تلك الأشياء اليومية،
to feel them, and try to improve upon them.
و استشعارها ومحاولة تحسينها.
For example, see this piece of fruit?
فمثلا، هل ترون هذه الفاكهة؟
See this little sticker?
وهل ترون الملصق الصغير؟
That sticker wasn't there when I was a kid.
لم يكن هذا الملصق هنا في صغري.
But somewhere as the years passed,
لكن في مكان ووقت ما
someone had the bright idea to put that sticker on the fruit.
خطرت على بال أحدهم فكرة عبقرية بوضع ملصق على الفاكهة.
Why?
لماذا؟
So it could be easier for us
ربما لتسهيل الأمر علينا
to check out at the grocery counter.
لدفع ثمنها عند البقال.
Well that's great,
حسناً هذا رائع،
we can get in and out of the store quickly.
يمكننا التسوق بشكل أسرع.
But now, there's a new problem.
لكن الآن هناك مشكل جديد.
When we get home and we're hungry
عندما نعود للمنزل جائعين
and we see this ripe, juicy piece of fruit on the counter,
ونشاهد تلك الفاكهة الشهية والناضجة فوق المنضدة
we just want to pick it up and eat it.
نرغب فقط في أخذها وأكلها.
Except now, we have to look for this little sticker.
لكن اليوم، علينا البحث على الملصق الصغير.
And dig at it with our nails, damaging the flesh.
ومحاولة اقتلاعه بأظافرنا متلفين الفاكهة.
Then rolling up that sticker --
ثم لف ذلك الملصق --
you know what I mean.
تعرفون ما أقصده.
And then trying to flick it off your fingers.
ثم محاولة نزعه من على أصابعكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's not fun,
هذا ليس ممتعاً،
not at all.
على الإطلاق.
But something interesting happened.
لكن حدث أمر مثير للاهتمام.
See the first time you did it, you probably felt those feelings.
أول مرة قمتم بذلك، شعرتم على الأرجح
You just wanted to eat the piece of fruit.
أنكم ترغبون فقط في أكل تلك الفاكهة.
You felt upset.
شعرتم بالغضب.
You just wanted to dive in.
وتريدون فقط قضمها.
By the 10th time,
لكن في المرة العاشرة
you started to become less upset
بدأ غضبكم يخمد
and you just started peeling the label off.
وبدأتم تزيلون الملصق.
By the 100th time, at least for me,
وفي المرة المائة، على الأقل بالنسبة لي،
I became numb to it.
لم أعد أفكر في الأمر.
I simply picked up the piece of fruit,
أصبحت آخذ فاكهتي
dug at it with my nails, tried to flick it off,
وأقتلع الملصق بأظافري وأحاول رميه،
and then wondered,
فتساءلت بعدها:
"Was there another sticker?"
"هل هناك ملصق غيره؟"
So why is that?
إذاً لماذا؟
Why do we get used to everyday things?
لم نتأقلم مع الأشياء اليومية؟
Well as human beings, we have limited brain power.
كبشر نمتلك قدرة عقلية محدودة.
And so our brains encode the everyday things we do into habits
ولهذا يعمد عقلنا إلى برمجة الأمور اليومية في خانة العادات
so we can free up space to learn new things.
لنتيح المجال أمام تعلم أمور جديدة.
It's a process called habituation
إنها عملية تدعى بالاعتياد
and it's one of the most basic ways, as humans, we learn.
وهي واحدة من الطرق القاعدية التي نتعلمها كبشر.
Now, habituation isn't always bad.
الاعتيادية ليست دائماً أمراً سيئاً.
Remember learning to drive?
هل تتذكرون تعلمكم للسياقة؟
I sure do.
أنا أفعل.
Your hands clenched at 10 and 2 on the wheel,
يديكم على المقود عند 10 و2،
looking at every single object out there --
تراقبون كل شيء في الخارج --
the cars, the lights, the pedestrians.
السيارات والأضواء والراجلين.
It's a nerve-wracking experience.
إنها تجربة مثيرة للأعصاب.
So much so, that I couldn't even talk to anyone else in the car
بحيث لم أستطع حتى التحدث إلى أي أحد داخل السيارة
and I couldn't even listen to music.
بل حتى الاستماع إلى الموسيقى.
But then something interesting happened.
لكن حدث بعدها أمر مثير للاهتمام.
As the weeks went by, driving became easier and easier.
مع مرور الأسابيع، أصبحت القيادة أسهل فأسهل.
You habituated it.
لقد اعتدتموها.
It started to become fun and second nature.
بدأت تصبح أمراً ممتعاً وطبيعة مكتسبة.
And then, you could talk to your friends again
فتمكنتم بعدها من التحدث مع أصدقائكم والاستماع إلى الموسيقى.
So there's a good reason why our brains habituate things.
هناك سبب وجيه لاعتياد أدمغتنا على الأشياء.
If we didn't, we'd notice every little detail,
فإن لم تفعل ذلك سننتبه إلى كل تفصيل صغير
all the time.
بشكل دائم.
It would be exhausting,
وهذا سيكون مرهقاً،
and we'd have no time to learn about new things.
كما لن يكون لدينا الوقت لتعلم أشياء جديدة.
But sometimes, habituation isn't good.
لكن أحياناً، لا تكون الاعتيادية أمرا جيدًا.
If it stops us from noticing the problems that are around us,
إن كانت تمنعنا من ملاحظة المشاكل المحيطة بنا،
well, that's bad.
فسيكون ذلك مضراً.
And if it stops us from noticing and fixing those problems,
وإن منعتنا من ملاحظة وحل تلك المشاكل،
well, then that's really bad.
فإن ذلك أسوأ.
Comedians know all about this.
الممثلون يعرفون جيداً هذا الأمر.
Jerry Seinfeld's entire career was built on noticing those little details,
فقد بنى جيري ساينفيلد مساره الفني بالكامل على ملاحظة تلك التفاصيل الصغيرة،
those idiotic things we do every day that we don't even remember.
تلك الأمور الغبية التي نقوم بها يومياً دون تذكرها حتى.
He tells us about the time he visited his friends
إنه يخبرنا عن المرة التي زار فيها أصدقاءه
and he just wanted to take a comfortable shower.
وأراد أخذ حَمَّام مريح.
He'd reach out and grab the handle and turn it slightly one way,
مد يده إلى الصنبور وأداره ببطء في اتجاه واحد
and it was 100 degrees too hot.
وكان الماء جدُ ساخن.
And then he'd turn it the other way, and it was 100 degrees too cold.
فأداره بالاتجاه الآخر وكان جدُ بارد.
He just wanted a comfortable shower.
كان فقط يرغب في استحمامٍ مريح.
Now, we've all been there,
وقد جربنا جميعاً ذلك،
we just don't remember it.
لكننا ببساطة نسينا الأمر.
But Jerry did,
لكن جيري فعل،
and that's a comedian's job.
وهذا هو عمل الممثل.
But designers, innovators and entrepreneurs,
لكن عمل المصممين والمبتكرين وأصحاب المشروعات،
it's our job to not just notice those things,
ليس فقط ملاحظة تلك الأشياء
but to go one step further and try to fix them.
بل الذهاب لأبعد من ذلك ومحاولة حَلِّهَا.
See this, this person,
هل ترون الصورة،
this is Mary Anderson.
إنها ماري أندرسون.
In 1902 in New York City,
سنة 1902، نيويورك.
she was visiting.
زارت المدينة
It was a cold, wet, snowy day and she was warm inside a streetcar.
كان يوماً بارداً، وماطرًا تملؤه الثلوج وكانت هي تنعم بالدفء داخل التَّرَامْ.
As she was going to her destination, she noticed the driver opening the window
وبينما هي في طريقها لاحظت السائق يفتح النافذة
to clean off the excess snow so he could drive safely.
ليزيل الثلج من على الزجاج الأمامي ليقود بأمان.
When he opened the window, though, he let all this cold, wet air inside,
وبفتحه النافذة دخل الصقيع البارد
making all the passengers miserable.
فتعرض الركاب للبرد.
Now probably, most of those passengers just thought,
وعلى الأرجح فإن معظم أولئك الركاب كان لسان حالهم:
"It's a fact of life, he's got to open the window to clean it.
"ماذا عسانا نفعل، كان عليه فتح النافذة لإزالة الثلج.
That's just how it is."
هكذا هي الحياة."
But Mary didn't.
لكن ماري لم تفعل.
Mary thought,
تساءلت ماري،
"What if the diver could actually clean the windshield from the inside
"ماذا لو تمكن السائق من تنظيف الزجاج الأمامي من الداخل،
so that he could stay safe and drive
بحيث يمكنه أن يبقى في أمان ويقود
and the passengers could actually stay warm?"
ويحافظ الركاب على دفئهم؟"
So she picked up her sketchbook right then and there,
فأخذت دفتر رسمها في اللحظة والمكان عينه
and began drawing what would become the world's first windshield wiper.
وبدأت برسم ما سيصبح أول مساحة زجاج أمامي.
Now as a product designer, I try to learn from people like Mary
وكمصصم منتجات، أحاول التعلم من أشخاص كماري
to try to see the world the way it really is,
لمحاولة مشاهدة العالم كما هو،
not the way we think it is.
وليس بالشكل الذي نتصوره.
Why?
لماذا؟
Because it's easy to solve a problem that almost everyone sees.
لأنه من السهل حل مشكل يراه الجميع تقريباً.
But it's hard to solve a problem that almost no one sees.
لكن من الصعب فعل ذلك إن كان يغفل عنه معظم الناس.
Now some people think you're born with this ability
يعتقد البعض أنه إما أن تولدوا بهذه القدرة
or you're not,
أَوْ لاَ،
as if Mary Anderson was hardwired at birth to see the world more clearly.
وإذا كانت ماري أندرسون قد ولدت مزودة برؤية أوضح للعالم.
That wasn't the case for me.
هذه لم تكن حالتي.
I had to work at it.
كان عليَّ العمل لاكتسابها.
During my years at Apple,
خلال عملي في أبل،
Steve Jobs challenged us to come into work every day,
تحدانا ستيف جوبز أن نأتي كل يوم إلى العمل
to see our products through the eyes of the customer,
والنظر إلى منتجاتنا بعيون زبائننا،
the new customer,
الزبون الجديد،
the one that has fears and possible frustrations
الحامل للمخاوف والإحباطات المحتملة
and hopeful exhilaration that their new technology product
ولبهجة الأمل بأن يعمل جهازه الجديد
could work straightaway for them.
من الوهلة الأولى.
He called it staying beginners,
وسَمَّاه تحدي المبتدئ الأزلي،
and wanted to make sure that we focused on those tiny little details
وكان يود التحقق من أننا نركز على تلك التفاصيل الضئيلة
to make them faster, easier and seamless for the new customers.
لجعل المنتج أسرع وأسهل وأكثر سلاسة لأجل الزبون الجديد.
So I remember this clearly in the very earliest days of the iPod.
وأتذكر ذلك جيداً في بدايات الآي بود.
See, back in the '90s,
في التسعينيات،
being a gadget freak like I am,
أن تحب الآلات مثلي،
I would rush out to the store for the very, very latest gadget.
كنت أتنقل بين المحلات بحثاً عن آخر المستجدات.
I'd take all the time to get to the store,
كنت أمضي الوقت كله في الذهاب إلى المحل
I'd check out, I'd come back home, I'd start to unbox it.
والتحقق من كل شيء والعودة للمنزل لإفراغ العلبة.
And then, there was another little sticker:
لأجد مرة أخرى ملصقًا صغيرًا:
the one that said, "Charge before use."
يقول: "اشحن المنتج قبل الاستخدام."
What!
ماذا!
I can't believe it!
لا أصدق هذا!
I just spent all this time buying this product
استغرقت كل هذا الوقت في اقتنائه
and now I have to charge before use.
ومازال عليَّ شحنه قبل استخدامه.
I have to wait what felt like an eternity to use that coveted new toy.
كان عليَّ انتظار ما بدا لي مستحيلًا كالخلود لاستخدام لعبتي الجديدة.
It was crazy.
كان الأمر مجنوناً.
But you know what?
لكن هل تعرفون ماذا؟
Almost every product back then did that.
معظم المنتجات وقتها كانت بهذا الشكل.
When it had batteries in it,
إن كانت تعمل بالبطريات،
you had to charge it before you used it.
فعليك شحنها قبل استخدامها.
Well, Steve noticed that
وقد لاحظ ستيف ذلك
and he said,
وقال: "لن نسمح بذلك في منتجاتنا."
So what did we do?
فما الذي قمنا به؟
Typically, when you have a product that has a hard drive in it,
في العادة عندما يكون لديكم منتج بقرص صلب،
you run it for about 30 minutes in the factory
تشغلونه لمدة 30 دقيقة في المصنع
to make sure that hard drive's going to be working years later
للتأكد من أنه سيعمل جيداً لسنوات مقبلة
for the customer after they pull it out of the box.
عندما يخرجه الزبون من علبته.
What did we do instead?
شغلنا المنتج لأكثر من ساعتين.
We ran that product for over two hours.
وبدلا من ذلك ماذا فعلنا؟
Why?
لماذا؟
Well, first off, we could make a higher quality product,
لأنه سيساعدنا أساساً على بلوغ منتج بجودة عالية
be easy to test,
وعلى اختباره بسهولة
and make sure it was great for the customer.
والتأكد من أنه كان تجربة رائعة للزبون.
But most importantly,
ولكن الأهم من ذلك،
the battery came fully charged right out of the box,
هو أن المنتج يخرج من علبته ببطارية مشحونة بالكامل
ready to use.
جاهز للاستعمال.
So that customer, with all that exhilaration,
وعليه يمكن للزبون في غمرة إثارته
could just start using the product.
استخدام المنتج.
It was great, and it worked.
وكان ذلك رائعاً وناجحاً.
People liked it.
وأحبه الناس.
Today, almost every product that you get that's battery powered
واليوم، تقريباً كل منتج تخرجونه من علبته
comes out of the box fully charged,
يحتوي على بطارية مشحونة.
even if it doesn't have a hard drive.
حتى وإن لم يحتوي على قرص صلب.
But back then, we noticed that detail and we fixed it,
ولكن وقتها انتبهنا إلى هذا التفصيل ووجدنا الحل،
and now everyone else does that as well.
واليوم الكل يقوم بنفس الشيء.
No more, "Charge before use."
لا مزيد من "اشحن قبل الاستخدام."
So why am I telling you this?
لماذا أخبركم بهذا الأمر؟
Well, it's seeing the invisible problem,
لأن الأمر متعلق بملاحظة المشاكل الخفية،
not just the obvious problem, that's important,
وليس الواضحة منها فقط، وهذا أمر مهم،
not just for product design, but for everything we do.
ليس فقط في تصميم المنتجات، بل في كل شيء نفعله.
You see, there are invisible problems all around us,
فهناك العديد من المشاكل الخفية حولنا،
ones we can solve.
مشاكل يمكننا حلها.
But first we need to see them, to feel them.
لكن علينا أولاً ملاحظتها واستشعارها.
So, I'm hesitant to give you any tips
الحقيقة أني متردد في أن أقدم لكم أية نصائح في العلوم العصبية أو النفسية.
There's far too many experienced people in the TED community
لأن هناك العديد من الخبراء في مجتمع تيد
who would know much more about that than I ever will.
أكثر معرفة مني في هذين المجالين.
But let me leave you with a few tips that I do,
لكن اسمحوا لي بتقديم بعض النصائح التي أطبقها
that we all can do, to fight habituation.
والتي يمكننا جميعاً تطبيقها لمكافحة الاعتياد.
My first tip is to look broader.
نصيحتي الأولى، النظر إلى الأمور بشكل شامل.
You see, when you're tackling a problem,
عندما تقفون على مشكل
sometimes, there are a lot of steps that lead up to that problem.
أحياناً هناك الكثير من المراحل التي أدت إلى ذلك المشكل.
And sometimes, a lot of steps after it.
وأحياناً هناك مراحل أخرى تتبعه.
If you can take a step back and look broader,
إن أخذتم مسافة ونظرتم للأمر بشكل شامل
maybe you can change some of those boxes
قد تغيرون بعضاً من تلك المراحل السابقة للمشكل.
Maybe you can combine them.
أو قد تدمجونها.
Maybe you can remove them altogether to make that better.
أو قد تزيلونها جميعاً لتحسين الوضع.
Take thermostats, for instance.
ومثلاً، منظّمات الحرارة،
In the 1900s when they first came out, they were really simple to use.
عندما ظهرت سنة 1900، كانت سهلة الاستعمال،
You could turn them up or turn them down.
وكان يمكن فقط رفع أو خفض الحرارة.
People understood them.
تعلم الناس كيف يشغلونها.
But in the 1970s,
لكن سنة 1970،
the energy crisis struck,
ضربت أزمة الطاقة
and customers started thinking about how to save energy.
فبدأ الزبائن بالتفكير في كيفية الحفاظ على الطاقة.
So what happened?
فما الذي حدث؟
Thermostat designers decided to add a new step.
قرر مصمموا منظمات الحرارة إضافة مرحلة جديدة.
Instead of just turning up and down,
فعوض الاكتفاء برفع أو خفض الحرارة،
you now had to program it.
أصبح بإمكانكم اليوم برمجتها.
So you could tell it the temperature you wanted at a certain time.
فتحددون لها الحرارة التي تريدونها في وقت معين.
Now that seemed great.
يبدو ذلك رائعاً.
Every thermostat had started adding that feature.
بحيث أضيفت تلك الخاصية لجميع المنظمات الحرارية.
But it turned out that no one saved any energy.
لكن استهلاك الطاقة لم يتراجع.
Now, why is that?
والسبب في ذلك؟
Well, people couldn't predict the future.
لأنه لم يكن بمقدور الناس التكهن بالمستقبل.
They just didn't know how their weeks would change season to season,
لأنهم لم يعرفوا كيف سيتغير الطقس بتوالي الفصول والسنوات.
So no one was saving energy,
فلم يتمكن أحد من المحافظة على الطاقة.
and what happened?
والذي وقع؟
Thermostat designers went back to the drawing board
عاد مصمموا منظمات الحرارة إلى مخططاتهم
and they focused on that programming step.
وركزوا على مرحلة البرمجة.
They made better U.I.s,
وحسنوا من واجهة المستخدم
they made better documentation.
ومن دليل المستخدم.
But still, years later, people were not saving any energy
لكن وبعد سنوات، لم يتمكن الناس من الحفاظ على الطاقة،
because they just couldn't predict the future.
لأنه لا يمكنهم التنبؤ بالمستقبل.
So what did we do?
لذا، ما فعلناه؟
We put a machine-learning algorithm in instead of the programming
قمنا باستبدال البرمجة بخوارزمية للتعلم الآلي
that would simply watch when you turned it up and down,
تراقب متى ترفعون أو تخفضون الحرارة،
when you liked a certain temperature when you got up,
متى تفضلون رفع درجة حرارة معينة
or when you went away.
أو العكس.
And you know what?
وتعرفون ماذا؟
It worked.
لقد نجح الأمر.
People are saving energy without any programming.
حافظ الناس على الطاقة دون أية برمجة.
So, it doesn't matter what you're doing.
بغض النظر عما تفعلون.
If you take a step back and look at all the boxes,
إن أخذتم مسافة ونظرتم إلى جميع المراحل بشكل أشمل،
maybe there's a way to remove one or combine them
قد تكون هناك طريقة لتخطي إحداها أو الدمج بينها
so that you can make that process much simpler.
لتجعلوا العملية أبسط.
So that's my first tip: look broader.
إذاً، كانت هذه نصيحتي الأولى: النظر بشمولية.
For my second tip, it's to look closer.
أما نصيحتي الثانية: النظر عن قرب.
One of my greatest teachers was my grandfather.
كان جدي أحد معلميَّ العِظام.
He taught me all about the world.
علمني كل شيء عن العالم.
He taught me how things were built and how they were repaired,
علمني كيف بنيت الأشياء وكيف أصلحت،
the tools and techniques necessary to make a successful project.
الأدوات والتقنيات اللازمة لإنجاح أي مشروع.
I remember one story he told me about screws,
وأتذكر قصةً أخبرني بها حول البراغي
and about how you need to have the right screw for the right job.
وكيف أنكم بحاجة إلى البرغي المناسب للعمل المناسب.
There are many different screws:
هناك العديد من البراغي المختلفة:
wood screws, metal screws, anchors, concrete screws,
براغي خشبية ومعدنية ومرساة وملساء
the list went on and on.
والقائمة تطول.
Our job is to make products that are easy to install
وعملنا هو تصميم منتجات يسهل تركيبها
for all of our customs themselves without professionals.
من طرف جميع زبنائنا دون مساعدة المهنيين.
So what did we do?
لذا، ما فعلناه؟
I remembered that story that my grandfather told me,
تذكرت هذه القصة التي أخبرني بها جدي
and so we thought,
ففكرنا،
"How many different screws can we put in the box?
"كم برغياً مختلفاً يمكننا وضعه بالعلبة؟
Was it going to be two, three, four, five?
هل سنحتاج لاثنين أو ثلاثة أو أربعة أو خمسة؟
Because there's so many different wall types."
لأن هناك العديد من الجدران المختلفة."
So we thought about it, we optimized it,
ففكرنا وطورناها،
and we came up with three different screws to put in the box.
وقررنا وضع ثلاثة براغي مختلفة في العلبة.
We thought that was going to solve the problem.
واعتقدنا بأن هذا سيحل المشكل.
But it turned out, it didn't.
فتبين بأن الأمر لم ينته.
So we shipped the product,
فعرضنا المنتج للتسويق
and people weren't having a great experience.
لكنه لم يلق ترحيباً لدى الناس.
So what did we do?
لذا، ما فعلناه؟
We went back to the drawing board
عدنا فور علمنا بأن الأمر لم ينجح إلى مخططاتنا.
And we designed a special screw, a custom screw,
وصممنا برغيا خاصا، بمواصفات معينة،
much to the chagrin of our investors.
مما أغضب مستثمرينا المتسائلين:
They were like, "Why are you spending so much time on a little screw?
"لما تستغرقون كل هذا الوقت لتصميم برغي صغير؟
Get out there and sell more!"
قوموا ببيع المزيد!"
And we said, "We will sell more if we get this right."
وأخبرناهم: "سنبيع المزيد إن قمنا بهذا بالشكل الصحيح."
And it turned out, we did.
وتبين في النهاية أننا نجحنا.
With that custom little screw, there was just one screw in the box,
وبفضل هذا البرغي الصغير والخاص، احتجنا لبرغي واحد فقط بالعلبة
that was easy to mount and put on the wall.
سهل التركيب على الجدار.
So if we focus on those tiny details, the ones we may not see
لذا إن ركزنا على تلك التفاصيل الصغيرة، التي قد نغفل عنها،
and we look at them as we say,
وننظر إليها ونتساءل:
"Are those important
"هل هي مهمة؟
or is that the way we've always done it?
أو هل هذه هي الطريقة التي اتبعناها دائماً؟
Maybe there's a way to get rid of those."
ربما أن هناك طريقة لتخطيها؟"
So my last piece of advice is to think younger.
ونصيحتي الأخيرة هي التفكير الطفولي.
Every day, I'm confronted with interesting questions from my three young kids.
لأني أواجه يومياً الأسئلة المثيرة التي يطرحها أطفالي الثلاثة.
They come up with questions like,
أسئلة من قبيل:
Or, "Why don't my shoelaces have Velcro instead?"
أو "لماذا لا يوجد بحذائي فيلكرو بدل الأربطة؟
Sometimes, those questions are smart.
وأحياناً تكون تلك الأسئلة ذكية.
My son came to me the other day and I asked him,
مرة كنت مع ابني وطلبت منه،
"Go run out to the mailbox and check it."
"هلا ذهبت للتحقق من صندوق البريد."
He looked at me, puzzled, and said,
فنظر إليَّ مشدوهاً وقال:
"Why doesn't the mailbox just check itself and tell us when it has mail?" (Laughter)
"لما لا يتحقق الصندوق من نفسه ويخبرنا إذا كانت به أية رسالة؟"
I was like, "That's a pretty good question."
ففكرت: "هذا سؤال وجيه."
So, they can ask tons of questions
يمكن للأطفال أن يسألوا أطناناً من الأسئلة
and sometimes we find out we just don't have the right answers.
وأحياناً ندرك ببساطة أننا لا نملك الإجابات المناسبة.
We say, "Son, that's just the way the world works."
فنجيب: "بني، هكذا تجري الأمور."
So the more we're exposed to something,
لذا فكلما تعرضنا لشيء ما
the more we get used to it.
كلما اعتدنا عليه.
But kids haven't been around long enough
لكن الأطفال حديثي العهد بالعالم ليعتادوا على الأمور اليومية.
And so when they run into problems,
لذا عندما يواجهون أية مشاكل
they immediately try to solve them,
يحاولون فوراً حلها
and sometimes they find a better way,
وأحياناً يجدون طريقة أفضل،
and that way really is better.
وهذه حقاً أفضل طريقة للتفكير.
So my advice that we take to heart is to have young people on your team,
لذا، نصيحتي يجب أن يكون في فريق عملكم أشخاص شباب
or people with young minds.
أو أشخاص بعقلية شابة.
Because if you have those young minds,
لأن تلك العقول الشابة
they cause everyone in the room to think younger.
ستحفز الجميع للتفكير بعقلية شابة.
Picasso once said, "Every child is an artist.
قال بيكاسو: "كل طفل هو فنان.
The problem is when he or she grows up, is how to remain an artist."
لكن المشكل هو كيف سيحافظ على تلك الملكة الفنية عندما يكبر."
We all saw the world more clearly when we saw it for the first time,
كلنا بدا لنا العالم أوضح عندما رأيناه للمرة الأولى،
before a lifetime of habits got in the way.
قبل ركوب قطار العادات اليومية.
Our challenge is to get back there,
والتحدي هو العودة إلى تلك النظرة الفطرية
to feel that frustration,
للإحساس بتلك الخيبة
to see those little details,
لملاحظة تلك التفاصيل الصغيرة،
to look broader,
والنظر بشمولية
look closer,
وعن كثب
and to think younger
والتفكير فيها بطفولية
so we can stay beginners.
وبالتالي نظل مبتدئين.
It's not easy.
وهذا ليس سهلاً.
It requires us pushing back
فذلك يتطلب منا السباحة ضد واحد من أقوى التيارات التي تعطي للعالم معناه.
But if we do,
لكن إن نجحنا،
we could do some pretty amazing things.
سنتمكن من تحقيق أمور مدهشة.
For me, hopefully, that's better product design.
بالنسبة لي، وآمل ذلك، هو تصميم منتج أفضل.
For you, that could mean something else, something powerful.
بالنسبة لكم، قد يعني ذلك شيئًا آخر أقوى.
Our challenge is to wake up each day and say,
التحدي الذي يواجهنا، هو الاستيقاظ يومياً والتساؤل:
"How can I experience the world better?"
"كيف يمكنني استشعار العالم بشكل أفضل؟"
And if we do, maybe, just maybe,
وإن نجحنا،
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)